Okay,
we ready?
Good afternoon. I want to call the
meeting to order. Welcome to the
February 2nd, 2026 Public Service
Committee.
Um, as for uh some housekeeping items, I
would ask that the public and staff turn
your cell phones off or set to vibrate
and mute their devices if online.
Um, when making a public comment, please
clearly identify yourself. We are only
using one microphone today.
To make a public comment online, use the
raise hand function online.
And if you're in person, please approach
the podium and turn on the microphone by
pushing the green button or pushing the
button and it'll turn green and then
share with us your name. Um, we also
have no additional business will be
discussed following completion of the
agenda.
So, will the clerk please read the first
um action item?
>> Number six, ordinance third reading,
creating chapter 1.28, 28 administrative
inspection warrants establishing
authority for their issuance and
amending the municipal code of the city
of Cheyenne, Wyoming to authorize
certain city officials as specified to
apply for administrative inspection
warrants.
>> Could we have a staff report, please?
>> Madame Chairman, members of the public
service committee, for the record, I'm
Mayor Patrick Collins. We heard
testimony from members of the public
regarding a proposed administrative
inspection warrant ordinance. Concerns
regarding the fourth amendment of the
United States Constitution and Wyoming's
Constitution, why the fire chief asked
for this ordinance, the use of municipal
judges, defining abandoned buildings,
and just general distrust of government.
We took notes of the concerns and
working with Mr. Brody, our fire chief,
and our chief building official, we have
prepared a substitute ordinance we hope
will address most of the questions.
The substitute before you limit
administrative inspection warrants to
our fire chief, our fire marshal, and
the chief building official, and
warrants may be applied for only if the
property is damaged as a result of a
fire and a postfire inspection
investigation is required. A commercial
building requiring life safety
inspections by the fire department.
Maybe I'll just stop there for just a
second. We are required by
by law that we've passed the
international fire code to inspect
commercial buildings on an annual
semianual
basis um for life and safety issues. Um
so that's part of what we we need to be
able to do. Property has a building
permit filed by the property owner or
their agent and property that meets the
definition of being an abandoned
building. Article 1, section 4 of the
Wyoming Constitution reads, "The right
of the people to be secure in their
persons, houses, papers, and effects
against unreasonable searches, searches,
and seizures shall not be violated." But
then it goes on the second half of that
sentence, and it says, "No warrants
shall issue, but upon probable cause
supported by affidavit, particularly
describing the place to be searched or
the persons and things to be seized. I
believe the subsidy ordinance follows
the requirements provided in the state
constitution by requiring probable cause
supported by an affidavit and
particularly describing the place to be
searched.
The affidavit must describe the
applicant's authority and status in
applying for the warrant, the legal
authority requiring or authorizing the
inspection, the property be inspected,
and the purpose of the inspection,
including the basis on which the
profitable cause exists to inspect.
It gives a process for determining if
probable cause exists.
Reasonable legislative or administrative
standards for conducting a routine
periodic or area inspections are
satisfied with respect to the particular
property. I'd like you to think about
again those routine fire inspections or
fire investigations or building permits.
We have to go in and do the routine
parts of the follow-up inspections.
There's a probable cause to believe that
a condition of nonconformity, violation,
or other circumstances requiring
corrective action exists with respect to
the designated property. I'm thinking
about abandoned buildings. We need to
get in and check that out. An inspection
is reasonably necessary to determine,
discover, or verify the condition of the
property or structures for compliance
with applicable law. Again, building
permits or fire investigations would
fall under those categories. It also
defines the abandoned property as it's
unoccupied
and it's not just merely temporarily
vacant or seasonally unoccupied and
requires two or more of the four things
that has had its utilities terminated.
Essential fixtures have been removed.
It's been vandalized, has boarded up
openings or other visual con conditions
that when taken into account demonstrate
that the dwelling is not being useful
used for a useful purpose.
The affidavit must affirmatively state
that entry has been sawed and refused or
reason by reasonable efforts to contact
the property owner have been
unsuccessful.
And
we it further defines that uh that
unsuccessful means that we've attempted
to personally contact the owner at the
property. We've attempted to f to
contact them by telephone, email, or
other digital means and or we've sent a
certified letter to the property owner
at the last known address reflected in
the county records or other reliable
sources.
The substitute requires a municipal
judge to determine based on the sworn
affidavit whether probable cause exists
and sufficient grounds exist for the
granting of the application.
If the municipal judge finds that the
probable cause um and all other
requirements imposed by this ordinance
have been satisfied, the judge shall
issue the warrant and that warrant shall
include the name and title of those
authorized to execute it, the specific
property, area, premises or building to
be inspected, the scope and purpose of
the inspection, and the warrant that the
warrant may only be executed during
reasonable hours and in a reasonable
manner or um at another time if the
judge determines that's appropriate.
The substitute also talks about the how
the warrants should be executed. First,
before execution, the person authorized
shall um make reasonable efforts to
present their credentials and state
their authority. State the purpose of
the warrant and requested give the copy
of the warrant to um uh the homeowner or
the property owner. The substitute
expressly forbids no knock warrants
except when executing warrant on an
abandoned property. Don't know how you
give somebody who's abandoned notice.
Allows the inclusion of law enforcement
if it's reasonably necessary to ensure
the safety of personnel or the security
of the property. And also the warrants
expire 10 days after the issuance unless
the judge can extend it but only up to 5
days. And a couple of examples why the
fire chief and chief building official
have asked for administrative warrants.
Again, I was I I spoke earlier. Uh the
city has adopted the international fire
codes and if we don't do it, the state
will do it. And one of the requirements
is that the commercial buildings, all
commercial buildings have to be
inspected on a regular basis. Chief Doc
has shared that a number of instances
where property owners have not wanted to
allow inspectors access to do these
necessary inspections. But to be fair,
he's pretty persistent and he stated
over time eventually they've been with
education, they've gotten most of them
to comply.
We recently had a fire in a single
family home and our firefighters were
able to rescue a gentleman from a
burning home. Unfortunately, he died
later of those injuries, but because the
owner died and we can't get permission
to enter the home to determine the cause
of the fire. And my question is, was it
a terrible accident or something that
needs more investigation?
We all know of a recent incident when a
property owner applied for a building
permit and they would not allow building
officials to verify the work was done to
code.
The neighbors have contact all of us uh
about their concerns, but we don't have
a mechanism to enforce a permit or to
address the neighbors concerns.
And we have abandoned buildings, many
abandoned buildings in our community,
and they come with health and safety
issues over time. And I think they're
really a detriment to our neighborhoods.
One of the challenges of finding the the
owner of the property and getting
permission to inspect and properly board
up the properties. We find some are
foreclosed upon and finding the mortgage
company and somebody to give permission
is challenging. Some properties had
owners die. They passed away and we
can't find the successor owners to get
permission. Uh and we have many more
types or examples like this. So, Madam
Chairman, I'm happy to answer any
questions uh about policy and our
attorney, Mr. Brody, can answer any
legal questions you might have, but I
would ask for your support of the
substitute.
microphone.
>> Your microphone.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Do we have
questions from the committee?
>> Okay, then we'll go out to the public
for public comment. Is there anyone that
would like to uh comment on this
ordinance?
Good afternoon, members of the
committee. My name is Patricia McCoy. I
am here today to speak on behalf of
myself and many other citizens who value
the sanctity of the home and the
protections of article 1, section 4 of
the Wyoming Constitution. While there
has been talk of postponement, we
believe the issues with this ordinance
are clear enough to be fixed today.
Specifically, section 1.28.020B
is a complete non-starter for the people
of Cheyenne. This section allows a city
official to bypass requirement to
present credentials or provide notice if
they reasonably believe notice would
frustrate the purpose of the inspection.
This is a suspicionless entry clause. It
turns an administrative inspection into
a tactical entry. Under the Wyoming
Supreme Court's reasonableness test, a
search must be no more intrusive than
necessary. Entering a home or property
without notice when no criminal activity
is a foot is is the definition of
unreasonable. We will not accept and we
will continue to fight any ordinance
that moves forward with section B
included. Furthermore, I am here to
state my full and unwavering support for
some amendments that will be presented.
I'm assuming later because we didn't get
to them yet. um that I know one of your
members has. These amendments provide
the only path forward for a
constitutionally sound ordinance.
Saying that something is reasonable or
objective in this wording is where your
skeleton key comes. It's what gives them
an an access to every building in the
city limits. Whether you think it does
or not,
someone could say, "Oh, this is
reasonable today." But someone tomorrow
could say, "That's not reasonable."
It has to be legal. It has to be
verifiable. This right now is not as
long as section B is in it. So, I would
humbly request that section B be
completely removed. Thank you.
>> Go ahead.
Thank you, Miss McCoy.
>> Dr. Emmens and members of the public
service committee. Thank you for the
opportunity to address the public
service committee hearing today
regarding administrative warrants being
considered. My name is John Frank. I
live in Saddle Ridge here in Cheyenne.
If my words are a bit slurred, I
recently had some oral surgery and I'm
wearing an appliance in the roof of my
mouth.
I would like to focus my comments on one
area also on section 18 or excuse me
1.28.02
grounds for issuance and also in
particular section B.
While I agree with Councilwoman
Eldrich's proposed changes, I propose a
broader change to this section.
My primary objection lies with paragraph
one of this section in particular with
the routine periodic or area inspection.
I've copies of the changes that I
propose and will be happy to have them
distributed to members of the committee.
I propose replacing section 1.28.020
grounds for issuance section B in its
entirety with the following. Again
1.28.02 020 grounds for issuance B.
Probable cause shall exist only if one.
There is probable cause to believe that
a condition of nonconformity,
violation of other law, or other
circumstances requiring corrective
actions exist with respect to the
designated property that causes an
immediate risk to public health and
safety. or two. If there is an active
permit issued by the city for the
designated property and the owner or
permit have refused access to inspectors
to the portions of the property subject
to the active permit.
My observations of previous hearings is
a major concern from the public's
perspective was concerning the overreach
of these proposed warrants. Also, from
the city council's perspective, with the
exception of one city councilman, all of
the rest of the re concerns focused on
abandoned properties.
My request is to focus these warrants
very narrowly on what seemed to me to be
the predominant concern, that being
abandoned properties, truly abandoned
properties.
Thank you for your time and
consideration.
>> Thank you, Mr. Frank.
Uh good afternoon, Madam Chairman,
members of the committee. Uh thank you
for this opportunity. My name is Steve
Millia from uh Shine, Wyoming here. As
uh I was reading over this, I'm going
darn this sounds pretty darn good. I
mean, it's well written. It's got the
city code in here. It's got the fire
chief, the uh uh
fire marshal, etc. All these uh state
statutes and uh did a pretty good job
all the way through.
Then they got that 1.28.020
grounds for issuance and then all the
red flags popped up as was stated by Mr.
Young and Miss McCoy. uh probable cause
reasonable
legislative or administrative standards
we can now Miss McCory talked about
reasonable and I would agree with her on
what's reasonable and then what got me
was routine periodic or area inspection
what is a routine periodic especially an
area inspection are you going to take uh
western hills and say oh this is an area
we're going to going to go through uh
periodic is it like once every 3 months
uh to me, I thought, well, everything
else I thought was really well written,
seriously speaking. And then this, in my
mind, just negated all that and said,
okay, that's really nice, but we're
going to do an area inspection. So, end
of story. Here we go. And there was
nothing in here that I saw that said, u
maybe my memory isn't as good as it
should be, but I didn't see anything
here that said residential homes are
explicitly uh exempt that are already
up. And I can understand codes need to
be followed. the codes are not followed.
That's bad. But uh when it comes to the
probable cause saying well we're just
going to conduct a routine inspection
where why uh everything else seemed
really really good. I know that there's
a an amendment coming forward about u
immediate and imminent uh health and
safety which is good. If it's imminent
that that's that's good. So I would
support that as it's going to be
presented later on. Uh but other than
that I thought seriously when I read
this I thought you guys did a really
good job. I mean all the way up through
and then we get to uh
1.028020
section B number one two and three and I
thought delete all that and I think you
have a really good uh
ordinance proposed and whatnot and I
appreciate that you are concerned about
our and uh thank you for that. So
if we got rid of B1 at least, if not two
and three, I think there would be a zip
document all the way through start to
finish. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Good afternoon, members of the council.
Um, my name is Bailey Turner and I have
been a Wyoming resident for 27 years
with my family having been in Wyoming
for over a century. Today I'm here to
comment on the ordinance chapter 1.28
and the authority it proposes to grant.
As written, the ordinance authorizes
administrative inspection warrants to be
issued when consent is not obtained and
it explicitly allows these warrants to
be executed without the occupant
present.
The ordinance further relies on an
undefined standard of cause for these
inspections. A standard that is
acknowledged within the framework of
administrative law to be distinct from
and lower than traditional cause used in
criminal warrants. That distinction
matters
because the Fourth Amendment does not
only protect against criminal
investigations. It protects the home
itself against unreasonable entry by the
state regardless of purpose.
Chapter 1.28 shifts that protection by
normalizing entry based on compliance
objectives rather than individual
individualized suspicion and by placing
the determination of necessity largely
within the administrative process rather
than a narrowly constrained judicial
process.
Section 1.28020 28020
subsection C states that cause shall be
deemed to exist not only when there is
probable cause of violation but also
when reasonable legislative or
administrative standards for conducting
a routine periodic or area inspection
are satisfied stated in 1.28.020
subsection C paragraph 1 or an
inspection or investigation is
reasonably necessary to determine
discover or verify compliance 1.28.02 02
subsection B C paragraph 3. The phrase
reasonably necessary is undefined,
subjective, and untethered to evidence
of wrongdoing. This means a warrant may
be issued without suspicion, without a
complaint, and without a known violation
based solely on administrative judgment.
This is not the standard envisioned by
the fourth amendment which requires
warrants are based on particularized and
individualized suspicion not general
regulatory interest. Further, section
1.28040B
allows officials to bypass seeking
consent entirely if they claim
requesting consent might frustrate the
purpose of the inspection.
This exception is undefined and
expansive. It allows officials to avoid
resident interaction altogether based on
speculative inconvenience rather than
necessity.
Additionally, section 1.28.040
subsection B explicitly authorizes entry
without prior notice or presentation of
credentials when a property is
unoccupied or when notice is believed to
frustrate the inspection. This permits
government entry into private property
without the owner present, without
immediate accountability, and without an
opportunity to object. While the
ordinance includes a clause stating it
should not be applied inconsistently
with constitutional law, that language
does not cure the actual problem. The
ordinance itself establishes a warrant
framework that departs from
constitutional protections.
Passing this ordinance sets a dangerous
precedent not only for the city of
Cheyenne but for municipalities
nationwide. It normalizes the idea
administrative convenience can outweigh
fundamental privacy rights. Once that
threshold is lowered, it is not easily
raised. Again,
this council has a choice. You can
perceive the boundary between the city
of Cheyenne and the private home, or you
can lower it,
trusting that future administrations
will exercise the rate same restraint
you believe you would.
But history shows that trust is rarely
rewarded. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Miss Turner.
Good afternoon committee. Um Kathy
Sigleaniano. I didn't prepare anything
um but I will just agree with previous
speakers on section 1.28.020
um B. The people do not want that
section and I think you all know that
and I think the right thing to do would
be to remove it. Thank you.
Thank you. Is there anyone else that
would like to speak?
>> Is there anyone online?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sheldon, you can go ahead.
>> Hi. Yes. Uh Alan Sheldon, uh Ward 2. Um,
I actually don't want to extend this uh
comment too much longer since most of
the other individuals have actually
echoed what I was going to say. Um, I
would just um agree with them and uh
push for the uh committee to um remove
that section and to uh continue on with
amendments towards um more of a focus on
the abandoned buildings um and the
stated purpose for
um for the need for these warrants in
previous meetings. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Sheldon.
Mr. Mayor,
>> Madam Chairman, Patrick Collins,
I appreciate the testimony that we just
heard. Um, when you read the section B,
they talk about the reasonable um
routine
uh inspections, but I think you have to
read the
the entirety of of what we're doing. And
the entirety is you have to do all of
the things that are here. You you can
pick a a paragraph or whatever, but it
says that only four things can be uh
can be used for for a warrant. And that
is a u a postfire investigation, those
life safety inspections, uh somebody who
has a building permit or a an abandoned
property. And so if you if you look at
it through that perspective, those
routine um inspections are really
important because we have well let me go
back. The state of Wyoming passes the
international fire codes, the building
codes, and all of those things. We have
within we have to pass those within 180
days. If we don't pass them, the state
takes that responsibility away from us
and they'll do those inspections. Um and
and they'll do the enforcement of that.
Um
from my perspective, I think it's much
better if we do those inspections. So
this governing body has passed all of
those and so now we have that
responsibility. We have to go do routine
inspections of commercial buildings.
It's it's part of the requirement. If we
don't do that then the state's going to
take that away from us. Um when we have
a building permit we have routine
inspections we have to do at certain
points in that inspection process. We
have routine inspections we have to do.
Did they do the rough in electrical
correctly? Did they do the rough in uh
plumbing correctly? Is the foundation
installed correctly? So the safety of
that building is there. and then we come
back and we do a final inspection to
make sure that it meets all the health
and safety. Those are the routine things
we're talking about. But the important
thing to remember is it's only for those
four instances that we talked about. You
can't just look at one paragraph in this
whole orders. You have to look at the
entirety of the ordinance. And the
entirety of the ordinance, I think,
protects us from exactly a lot of things
we just heard. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Are there other
comments?
through you, Madam Chairman. Um, Michael
White, Larry County resident.
Um,
I have a question when the people refer
to the fire marshal or the that
jurisdiction starts at the state. So, a
couple questions I would have is the
current state fire marshal is Byron
Matthews. Um,
I'd be curious to know what the state
does in regards to inspections
of property that the owner hasn't given
permission to.
Number two, I respect the building
official and
fire chief here. I realized that
over the years it's been very
frustrating for this governing body to
be able to
put some teeth in an ordinance that
allows individuals that are code people
to do their job.
Example of that which many council
remember would be the hitch and post
area.
Unfortunately that was a long drawn out
process along with other projects. Um,
I'm not going to debate the fourth
amendment
in all regards. Uh, the fourth amendment
should be
commented on with respect to this group
by the city attorney or the attorney
general of the state of Wyoming.
I think what people get concerned with
is when
they have somebody going on their
property. I believe the intent
of any inspector, whether it's Bob or
the building official people, their
their intent is to do their job.
Unfortunately, there's a lot of um
roadblocks in the way. And we could talk
about that all day about the roadblocks
that
the building department and the fire
department and the council have had to
deal with in past incidences with a
number of properties. And I respect
the comments by the mayor, Mr. Collins,
that says the owner was dead and those
things are hard to assess a property.
But when we get into
property, we my issue is in somewhat is
are we looking at an administrative
judge or a judicial judge? And I guess
I'd have to have somebody clarify for
me.
Judges
do not normally give warrants without
probable cause. and we would hope as a
society that we continue that.
I believe that um there's been ample
time for comment and I
haven't been in town for a number of
months but this is a day I've actually
been so I'm going to give a my comments.
Sometimes when we get to these
ordinance, we get a lot of finetuning,
but at the end we get a lot of
individuals that state why they don't
want it. Um, I understand that
people believe that we do need it, but
let's go back to a little track record.
Governing body adopted the codes by the
state. The state recognizes the
international building code. the state
acknowledges the fire code. Those are
documents that we have used or I am
retired so I haven't used but those are
documents that can be used. I know the
frustration that will say it's not in a
timely manner or whatever so let's
change the rules.
I believe the rules are already there.
Now, it's frustrating for departments to
not get the results or do what they do
on a normal basis, but I would say the
rules are already here. And in all due
respect to the individuals working for
the city, I do not think this ordinance
is necessary. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. White.
Uh Bob Mason, Fire Marshall. Um Madame
Chair, committee members, I I just want
to address a couple things about uh the
fire code specifically. Uh specifically,
it only applies to commercial facilities
in the city of Cheyenne or residential
facilities being used for commercial
purposes such as daycarees, things of
that nature. Um,
so I keep hearing people talking about,
are we going to come do inspections
throughout Western Hills or some area of
town? That's not going to happen. Uh, we
can we we can't even get into the
commercial facilities that we're
responsible for on a on a regular basis.
Um, right now we're there buildings
there are commercial facilities in the
city of Cheyenne that haven't been
inspected in years and years just cuz we
don't have the manpower to get in them
on a on a regular basis. So, uh, any
fears that we're just going to direct
our attention to um, residential homes
is is it's just not going to happen and
we don't have the authority to do that
anyway. Uh now as far as the commercial
fire safety inspections go, that is
authorized in the in international fire
code that that is currently adopted. Uh
we do those um as often as as we can uh
as allowed uh there are very good
reasons that we go into buildings to do
uh conduct fire safety inspections. Uh
many buildings, commercial buildings
have fire safety systems in them. And if
and typically if if if a fire inspector
is not in there on somewhat of a routine
basis, those systems do fall fall do
over a period of time fall into various
um uh states of disrepair.
And we do have a lot of large
residential, you know, hotels, motel
that have those systems in them um that
it is the it is the owner's
responsibility to maintain those
systems. However, often they don't do
that unless constantly reminded due to
turnover of management, etc. So, if you
don't have a fire inspector in there
routinely doing those inspections in in
informing them of their
responsibilities, those things just
don't happen. And even in in in
buildings that don't have fire safety
systems, uh there are fire safety
features, exiting exit doors, things of
that nature that we go into just make
sure they're doing things properly and
that those buildings are safe to occupy
for the public. Now, I've been in the
fire marshall's office for about 13 and
a half years, and in the period of time
I've been in there, I've never had a a
business owner refuse me entry into a
building. Um, however, there has been
about a handful of times over the last
13 years that we have been required to
obtain or serve a notice and order on a
business owner. And what that is is if
they do deny us access into the
property, even short of an
administrative warrant, we do have a a
way to get in the property, which we
serve them a notice and order saying
that we're going to show up on the
property at a given date uh with a with
an officer. And if they deny us access,
they will be served a uh uh they will be
um served a um uh a notice to appear in
court, mandatory notice to appear in
court. And at that time they can explain
that to a judge why they're not um
allowing us in the property for to
conduct our lawful inspection. So, uh
that is a very that that it that is not
a pleasant way to have to do business uh
to deal with business owners, but we
have had to do that on occasion. U so
short an administrative warrant, we do
have ways to to do that, but uh it's
it's not really pleasant for anybody
involved.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Mason.
>> Madam Chairman,
>> u Mr. or Dr.
>> Renie, I have a couple question. I just
I want to confirm a couple things. The
um
routine periodic or area inspections
that are referred to in B1 are just for
commercial only. Correct.
>> Yeah, that's just for commercial
properties.
>> And I've had over the years had a couple
inspections of my business. Um, you guys
just showed up and said, "Hey, we need
to do an inspection." And essentially
what what I found they were checking
for, are my smoke detectors working? Do
I have fire doors where I'm supposed to
have fire doors? Are the fire doors
closed and not propped open? And do I
have a working fire extinguisher in my
office? And I would think, and that's
pretty much standard what you're looking
for in a business, I take it. uh for a
small business like that and there are
other things we're looking for improper
use of extension cords or space heaters,
things of that nature, but but that
you're you're right on track.
>> Okay. So, I just to me um I don't I you
know may intend to amend this slightly
later to make sure it refers only to
commercial properties if that'll make
people feel better. But as a as a
business owner, I don't look at that as
being egregious. And I would think that
my patients would want to know that I
have, you know, everything is done
properly. So if a fire does break out in
my office that that they would be safe,
that they would have egress and be able
to get out of there. So I guess some of
those people that said this wasn't
right. You know, if you might let me
know why you wouldn't want to be in a
business that was safe.
>> If I could add one more thing, and I I
said this is generally limited to
commercial properties. There are on
occasion instances we will be show up at
a at a single family residence and that
would be in the case of a complaint
about a fire pit, smoke, things of that
nature, more of a nuisance call. And
there are also uh um nuisance
enforcement uh officers for the city of
Cheyenne, but often the the fire
department is called out for say a fire
pit. So that that is another that is one
reason we would be required to show up
at a single family residence for uh and
and to my knowledge we've never been
denied access for something of that
nature either. So but that could
>> madam chairwoman through you but again
that's exceptional. It's not routine
periodic or area inspected.
>> You're correct. Thank you.
>> Thank you Mr. Mason. Okay. Anybody else?
Oh, yeah.
>> Uh, Mr. Crossman, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> All right.
Thank you, Colin Crossman, Ward One. Um
so I heard interesting thing earlier
with the mayor saying um that the
reasonable uh area routine or the
periodic routine area inspection is for
these commercial things and also for um
uh for dealing with permits uh open
permits you know if you have to do an
inspection because you have an open
building permit um I don't I don't
really think that you need that
additional power however um uh and also
think that there is a uh uh a substitute
coming um from one of the council
members that is uh fully satisfactory
for all of these things. But if it's
necessary to leave this language in
there, uh, a modification would be
reasonable legislative or administrative
standards for conducting a routine
periodic or area inspection are
satisfied with respect to the particular
non-residential or commercial property
and also solely related a pertinent or
incidental to an open building permit.
And I believe that the other elements
that were added will satisfy what the
fire chief was just talking about. So if
if it is believed that a building
inspector
doesn't have the authority to inspect an
open building permit, you know, that can
be solved in a manner that leaves
residential and buildings without an
open building permit aside. Um because
after all, if you have an open building
permit, you've invited the inspectors on
your land for the purposes of the
building permit. So, um I don't really
have a problem with them coming on on
land or if they feel like they need a
warrant to make that inspection, the
ability to get the warrant in this
situation where there is an open
building permit. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you, sir.
Okay.
So, I'm going to say public comment is
closed on that. What is the pleasure of
the committee? Madam Chairwoman,
>> Dr. Renie.
>> So to get this started, I would to move
to approve the ordinance on third and
final reading.
>> Is there second for the sake of
conversation?
>> Madame Chairwoman.
>> Go ahead, Dr. Renie.
>> I would move to amend by substitute
dated January 30th, 2026.
>> A second. Madame Chairwoman, if I may.
>> Yes, go ahead.
>> Um, do you substitute
is much more constrained and narrowed
narrower focus than the ordinance we've
been looking at so far. And it
essentially delineates the only time
that
we can um issue an administrative
warrant is for the four things the mayor
stated earlier. abandoned homes, open
building permits
essentially
and refusal for like fire from the fire
department. And then I have a couple
questions, madam chairman, that I would
like to ask
our attorney if I may.
>> Go ahead.
>> So through you, Madam Chairwoman, to Mr.
Brody
in looking this I got it highlighted
somewhere but one of the things brought
up was we weren't complying with state
statute.
So in 1.28.030
second line it says based upon a sworn
affidavit. So at this point I think that
does that bring us in compliance with
state statute.
>> Uh madam chairman John Brody city
attorney. Um, I think the base response
is yes. Um, however, that affidavit
requirement is under the Wyoming
constitution, not state statute.
>> Correct. Thank you for pointing that
out, but that's that was my reference
that we were now in compliance with the
state constitution.
>> Uh, that is accurate.
>> Okay. My second question was, and I've
had some people comment to me about
this, um, is that they would rather see
the warrant issued from district court,
not municipal court. and their
contention is that the municipal court
judge is an employee of the city. So,
he's more more likely to comply with a
request from the city. Um, personally,
I've, you know, told some of those
people, I we have as council members,
and I don't know about the
administration, but we very have very
little contact or dealings with the
municipal court, and I may not even
recognize some of our municipal court
judges if I saw them. But I did ask our
district attorney last week if in the um
event
a municipal warrant was or an
administrative warrant was required
based upon municipal code
what were the consequences if it went to
district court and you know can we even
do that and I was told um again by our
district attorney that one it'd probably
take a heck of a lot longer
um which is probably true and may not be
a big deal but secondly
I was told that in all likelihood it
would not even be looked at by the
district courts simply be or district
judges simply because they are dealing
with state statute and not municipal
ordinances. So Mr. Brody, I guess I
would take her statement as accurate. I
do not know why it would not be, but do
you have an opinion on that part of it?
>> U Madame Chairman or chairwoman, excuse
me, uh Dr. I I would just say that your
comments reflect the research we've
conducted in my office. Um even if we
could technically get a warrant in front
of a district court judge, there would
be nothing requiring that judge to give
it any sort of legal authority or or
import.
Um municipal courts uh especially for
first class cities have exclusive
jurisdiction over ordinance. Um so you
know I think from a real fundamental
legal level a circuit court a district
court doesn't even have jurisdiction uh
in this case.
>> Okay. Thank you, Madam Thank you, Madam
Chair, and thank you, Mr. Brody. I guess
my comments on that were I thought
people had that was a legitimate
question. You know, I understand they're
wanting to have a little separation, but
in what research I've done on that
separation may not be possible.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Um,
Chairwoman Emmens, I I would like to um
make an amendment, please. I'm going to
I have a series of these and so I'll
start with the uh on the last page under
section four. We'll start at the back
and work to the front.
Um I'd like to add a section four um
that an incident report will be provided
to the council after each administrative
warrant is activated.
>> Second that.
>> Okay. So we have a first and a second to
Could you repeat that, Dr. Albridge?
>> Sure. and that an an incident report
will be provided to the council after
each administrative warrant is
activated.
>> Okay. So, we will we have a second. So,
we'll go back out to uh the audience for
any public comment.
>> Uh John Brody, city attorney. I would
just ask if if the amendment could be
worded in um terms of executed um
because once the warrant has been
executed then that process is complete
and then we would have a full report um
to provide the city council. this, Madam
Chairwoman.
>> Yes,
>> I was going to bring that up.
Ask my colleague that we had talked
about doing this before the meeting
started. And my perception when I
suggested it was that we would get an
incident report once that would tell us
why why the warrant was executed, what
the need for it was, and what the
resolution was. So, I like the executed
language better.
Jennifer, did you Okay. The friendly
amendment, I would accept that.
>> We don't normally do friendly
amendments, but
>> Go ahead, Kathy.
>> Hi, Kathy Cigleaniano. Um, I would
agree. I think transparency is super
important from any elected body. So, I
like the amendment.
>> Thank you. Any other comments?
race.
>> Hello, Bailey Turner. Um,
in chapter 1.28 at 1.280
10 subsection A, it states
>> order. Madam, Madam Chairwoman,
>> um, we're on creating a new section 4,
so the discussion needs to be on that.
So, Miss Turner, is this specific to
that that amendment?
>> Unfortunately, no, but I feel like
>> we'll probably bring more amendments
coming. Okay,
>> go ahead.
>> Thank you, Chairwoman. My name is
Patricia McCoy. I would support that
amendment. It does give transparency and
it holds people accountable if things
didn't go right like they should have in
the process. So, I would support that.
>> Thank you. Jennifer, you have somebody
online.
M Mr. Smith, would you like to speak on
the amendment?
Okay.
Anyone else?
Okay, then we'll come back to the
committee for any comments.
>> Go ahead,
>> Madame Chairman. Could you um have that
repeated with the friendly amendment I
believe I heard was uh included.
>> Thank you, Mr. Layborn. Jennifer, can
you repeat that?
I'm gonna uh following an executed
incident, a report will be provided to
the council.
>> Madam Chairman,
>> excuse me.
>> I just was asking if council could maybe
help us help us with language. Pardon
me.
>> Um,
for one thing, it's not clear who's
going to make this report.
Is it going to be uh the department that
uh executes it? Is it going to be the
court itself?
Uh it's certainly uh
a little bit different, but uh the
concerns been raised, but I'm not
certain um that language is specific
enough to
uh who would be doing this and what what
that report would include.
So, um, if I could get some help with
that, uh, I'd appreciate it.
>> Thank you, Mr. Laybourne. Dr. Aldridge,
would you like to restate your motion?
>> Well, what I had written down is that an
incident report will be provided to the
council um, after each administrative
warrant is and we it's agreed on
changing to executed. Um, I understand
my colleagues concern about who's going
to provide the report and what will be
included in that. Um,
I guess my thought is that if we pass
this in
generalities that before the final
reading on Monday night that that could
be identified as to which uh department
and what would specifically be included
in that report. Is that not correct?
U Dr. Aldrich. Well, go ahead, Dr.
Mr. Lelay.
>> I appreciate the promotion,
>> but uh I think that's the point here. Um
we don't want any confusion if and when
this becomes law and it appears to me
that this would be the responsibility of
our administrative assistant in the
council office. Um well
well who is going to provide the report
and uh and when when does it come to us?
I I and I and I do understand that uh
that specific could be worked out later
but um perhaps we could get some advice
from the people who would be uh asking
for that warrant and certainly uh the
court and how they report such a matter
I think has to be specific. It can't be
general. So maybe Mr. Brody can help me.
>> Mr. Brody, could you give us some
guidance?
>> Uh, Madam Chairwoman, I I guess my
recommendation would be that since the
the wish, it seems of the amendment is
that for that report to be generated
upon the execution of each warrant that
the building official or the fire chief
or the fire marshal, those individuals
would be responsible for gathering that
information and submitting it to you
because it's on a one forone basis on
when you want to be informed.
>> Thank you. and I can work if you'd like
on some language to tighten that up for
Monday to make it more clear uh in that
new section that's going to be inserted.
>> Dr. Renie, did you
>> No, Madam Chairman, that's exactly what
I was about to say is that the report
should come from the body that requested
the warrant and executed the warrant.
>> Okay. So, based on that, are we ready
for a vote?
So all those in favor of the amendment
to um provide
uh report once
an action is ex executed.
Please um signify by saying I
>> I
>> and any opposed.
>> Okay, that vote carries.
>> Okay, Chairwoman Emmens. Um the next
amendment I would like to make is um the
addition to 1.28 28020C3.
And um that
paragraph currently talks about if the
attempts described in paragraphs one and
two of the subsection are unsuccessful,
transmission of a certified letter to
the property owner at the owner's last
known address as reflected in county
records or other reliable sources is how
it currently reads. And I would like
that to um in have the addition of the
warrant shall not be issued unless a
certified mailing has been received as
indicated by the postal service where
seven business days have elapsed. Um
I'll explain after I get a second.
>> Is there a second to that amendment?
>> Madam chair and I'll second so that we
can discuss it.
>> Okay. So we have a first and a second.
So, we'll go back out for
>> Can I explain it?
>> Yes, you can. I'm sorry.
>> That's okay. This is my first meeting
doing this, you guys. So,
>> you're doing great.
>> Thank you for being home.
>> The um reason for that addition is um
and Mr. Bloom may be able to confirm
this, but we recently had a situation
where an individual was mailed a
certified letter and that certified
letter uh did not reach the individual
in a timely fashion and I believe in
fact it was returned to the uh planning
office um after the fact. Um Seth's
shaking his head. Yes. So, um I just I
think that while we would always hope
that the US Postal Service delivers in
rain, snow or you know whatever other
condition, um for some reason that
didn't get that didn't occur. And so
this would just be one more safeguard
that uh we would wait uh either get the
confirmation from the postal service
that that certified uh mail had been uh
received or seven business days from the
time it had been sent. And that's only
remember that this only goes into effect
um if the other uh attempts in listed in
C1 and C2 were not successful. The
certified letter is the last ditch
effort to contact the property owner. So
>> thank you Dr. Aldridge. Okay, now go
back out to the public for any comments
on that.
I think we're going to become really
good friends today. My name is Patricia
McCoy. I do support this. Um, there have
been times where I personally have been
sent things certified mail and not
received them or sent certified mail
myself and not been able to verify that
it was actually received. So, I think
having that safeguard in there is a
really good thing to make sure that
we're doing all avenues to try and reach
the the owner of the property. Thank
you. Thank you, Miss McCoy.
I will just say ditto Kathy Ciganiano.
>> Thank you.
Anybody else?
And anyone online?
>> Hi, my name is Seth. I'm with the City
of Shine Planning and Development
Department. Um, just a note with
certified mailing. We do that a lot in
our planning and development department.
And unfortunately, there are people who
will actively refuse a certified letter.
And so I'm just making sure that we are
clear as to what the situation involves
when someone refuses to accept a
certified letter. Um I don't think we
want the process to stop if someone
refuses the letter. I understand that
sometimes gets lost. That happens. But
if someone's actively contacted by the
postal department and refuses the
letter, I I I don't necessarily want
processes to stop because if they're
avoiding us for all other reasons, they
may be avoiding us there as well. Thank
you,
>> Dr. Chairwoman Emmens. Uh that is why
the additional piece is uh implemented
there that says
um that um
where how it reads that the warrant
shall not be issued unless the certified
mailing has been received as indicated
by the postal service or seven business
days have elapsed. So um it would be
delayed the seven days while we're
waiting for that uh receipt of um
receiving that mail. But at the end of 7
days, we move forward whether we have
that signed um
uh certified mail receipt or not.
>> Okay. Is there any other public comment?
>> Okay.
Committee members,
>> madam chairwoman.
>> Yes. I guess I'm I would like to know
once we send out a letter how long we
actually wait to see if it's been
received
and what the impact of this amendment
would be on our
um current pro processes. To me, it
doesn't seem like seems there'd be a
little bit of lapse of time in there
anyway since they're busy. that I'd like
to hear either um from the building
department, the fire department and
andor both as to does this have any
impact on their operations.
>> Uh Mr. Chairwoman, um through you to Dr.
Renie, uh Ton Palmer, chief building
official, city of Cheyenne. Um,
currently the uh property maintenance
code when we're talking specifically
about abandoned buildings has this
language specifically called in out
within it um that requires us to send
this certified letter. We're required to
wait for that receipt. If we do not get
a response from the uh owner of the
property, the building official is then
required to post that non-receipt.
Typically I I personally leave at least
10 business days, 2 weeks. That is
adjustable. It is, you know, allowed to
be up to the discretion of the building
official as to how long that would
remain posted, but that is clearly
outlined within the property maintenance
code for abandoned buildings.
>> So I I have a question. So is this
duplicative then?
>> U Madam Chairwoman, I would not call it
duplicitative. I would call it in line
with it does not affect the building
department adversely.
>> Thank you.
>> Madam Chair, Andrew Dhorn, fire chief.
Um,
so the fire code really as far as
abandoned buildings refers back to the
international building code. Um, so we
kind of take our lead from them when it
comes to this. It does not speak
specifically to certified mailings. So
just to answer answer that question,
>> Dr. Inny,
>> Madame Chairwoman, to Chief Dyhorn,
what so with abandoned buildings, I
mean, they've been there for a while. So
I understand waiting another week and a
half is not a big deal. However, if an
instance where there's a fire and you
need to and you want to do an
investigation,
is there an impact on on this time
frame? um if you have to wait to get in
there and do an investigation.
>> Uh you madam chair. Um yes, potentially
there could be an impact to chain of
custody of evidence, things like that
depending on the security of the
building. Uh however, if we start or
initiate our investigation during the
exigent circumstances that were there,
um hopefully there is a plan put in
place by our fire marshall and our
investigators to um continue to
investigate or not turn that property
back over until we can get a pretty
confirmed answer or for sure secure the
building in a sense. Um there could be a
loss of chain of custody of evidence um
just depending on on the the state of
the the building and depending on the
delay of us getting back in there.
>> Thank you, Chief. Thank Thank you, Madam
Chairwoman.
>> Dr. Alrich,
>> uh Chairwoman Amends, I did have a
question for Chief Dyorn. Um I'm
guessing that currently uh the this is
for Andy. Currently the process uh that
you're currently using that there are
times um under the current tools you
have to use that you have a length of
time that is longer than 7 days that may
impact your chain of custody as well. Is
that correct?
Do we have a time that could sorry
through you madam chair
>> under the current process that you're
currently using to access those
properties is are there instances where
that extends beyond this week and a half
that impacts your chain of custody
currently?
>> Um potentially yes.
>> Thank you.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. Go ahead, Seth.
>> Madam Chair, Seth is the planning and
development department. There was a
question regarding how fast certified
mail usually takes. Um, I would say that
given our experience with annexations,
um, certified mailing lo if the mailing
address is a local individual, so not an
out ofstate property owner. Um, we often
get responses that the mail has been
received within a day or the next day,
basically the next day after we mailed
it. Um, so within 24 hours of when we
mail it. Um and then um oftent times um
most of the letters are received uh
within uh three or four business days.
Um so uh seven business days or seven
days, seven calendar days um is within
the time frame of certainly of most
local mail. Um just as a point of
reference.
>> Thank you.
Okay. Any other questions or comments?
Okay. Um so we have a motion on the
table
um
in regard to um certified mail in seven
days.
All those in favor please sorry
>> did we end public comment
>> uh
>> I thought we did
>> do you have a comment?
>> Yes I do. Um and it's a question for the
chief. uh was just up here.
>> Um so chief, the mayor mentioned a case
that is evidently open at this time, an
occurrence of a death in a home with a
fire um that you are presently dealing
with. And this was uh brought forward as
an example of how uh difficult it can be
sometimes to contact
uh who whomever is the
either owner or has an interest in that
property. So, in in the case that the
mayor referenced,
how would this uh certified letter uh go
out to what I understand to be a
question of who it would go to, who
could you explain that series of events
and where it is right now?
>> Yes, sir. Through you, Madam Chair,
Andrew Dyorn, fire chief. Um, so yes, we
unfortunately had a a citizen pass away
um about a month after a fire that
occurred back in December. Um, he was
the uh owner of the property. Um, we do
have uh contact with his family members,
but it the property as far as the
ownership is an unknown unknown state at
this point. Um, we initially
investigated the fire as normal process.
Um, narrowed some things down, but
subsequent days um go by, witness
statements come in. Um so we the process
doesn't necessarily stop after we leave.
Um so in being in contact with um the
the homeowner's son um we have been able
to let them know like we're we're put us
putting notices on doors and we're
securing the building. Um but that's
about as far as as as where we have
taken it from from now. So our
investigation's kind of on kind of on
halt right now. Um, as far as speaking
towards sending a certified letter, I I
assume it would go to that property
homeowner who no longer uh is with us,
unfortunately.
So, I'm not sure to how to answer your
question because I'm not sure where that
would actually end up and probably
either be returned to sender as as we've
discussed or just we would never receive
anything of that nature.
>> Madam Chairman, um, thank you, Chief. I
think that it explains pretty much how
these various situations can uh be
unique and difficult and I don't
understand how
um
the actual process of that u certified
letter uh as I understand it needs to go
to the property owner and uh obviously
if the son is uh has some interest there
to be some time before the probate in
the entire disposition of the estate
would happen. So I really wonder if uh
this is uh um realistic in all
situations. I mean obviously it uh has
its use and we do it a lot with a
variety of things that uh the planning
office does but in this particular case
I don't know that it would be uh useful
uh and that would possibly I I think
that our our fire department is very
diligent in its follow-ups and uh
perhaps this wouldn't be as serious a
consideration, but I I do think that uh
if we keep piling on uh these kind of um
extras, it has the potential to uh
impact the department and their
investigation. Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Chairwoman Emmens, I would just point
out that in 1.28.020 020 section C. Um
that is this is only these certified
letters are only this um number three is
only done um if we have been un have
made a reasonable attempt to contact the
property owner or lawful occupant to
obtain consent and have been
unsuccessful. Obviously we know who the
occupant was even if he's now deceased.
Um, and it so and it's an attempt to
make personal contact at the location of
the property or with the property owner
and the the fire department in this
situation's already been in contact with
the son. It sounds like I'm not sure
that there would be any need to try and
send a certified letter in that case.
Um, so I think that this is um if we're
if we're going to leave uh C3 in, which
is the last ditch effort to contact
someone, um we've made a we've tried it
says we've already made an attempt to
make personal contact. We've made an
attempt to make contact by telephone,
electronic mail, or other reasonably
available digital means. That's in
section C1 and two. um at this point
having to send a letter a certified
letter which is already in being
proposed in C3
uh making sure that that has been either
received or 7 days have elapsed. I don't
know that that's going to um m make or
break um you know this this type of a
scenario. Um, I think it shows a good
faith effort on our part and it, uh,
provides a paper trail that I'm guessing
will, um, be added to the documentation
that would go forward then for an
administrative warrant to the judge. So,
um, thank you.
>> Thank you, Dr. Aldrich. Dr. Renie.
>> Madame Chairwoman, we've already heard
from our building department that they
already use a longer time frame than
seven working days that they routinely
use 10 working days or two weeks. Um so
I
so in this case it is I think somewhat
superolous.
And then secondly I do not wish to put
any further constraints on our
firefighters and or our fire
investigators.
um in their ability to do their jobs.
So, I will be opposed to the amendment.
>> Okay. Any further comments? Okay. So,
the amendment that was moved by Dr.
Aldrich and seconded by Dr. Renie is
that the warrant shall not be issued
unless the certified mailing has been
received as indicated by the postal
service or seven business days have
elapsed. All those in favor, please
signify. I
>> I
>> and those opposed.
>> No. No.
>> Okay. That amendment fails.
>> Chairwoman Emmens, I would like to make
an amendment um to
1.28.020
B2. And the reason I'm going to be
amending uh the 1.28.020
020 section at all rather than just
eliminating it is because what we heard
loud and clear from U public comment
three weeks ago I believe it was maybe
it's been four weeks now was that um we
needed to be able to prove probable
cause um there was a real concern that
um the initial um administrative warrant
ordinance did not um it assumed probable
cause um in talking with our city
attorney but it didn't spell it out. So,
I think this was an effort to make sure
that probable cause was spelled out um
which was one of the requests that we
heard early on from public comment.
So for that reason um my amendment is to
um the first amendment would be to
eliminate B1
um altogether uh that says reasonable
legislative or administrative standards
for conducting a routine periodic or
area inspection are satisfied with
respect to the particular property. Um
we've already established as the mayor
pointed out
in C4 or I'm sorry C section C of
1.28.01 010 that this is only if there's
an open building permit that the
individual has applied for um is one of
those conditions. So um or a regular
fire inspection. So that is my next
amendment.
>> So I'm sorry, Dr. Aldrich, can So you're
what you would like to do is eliminate
one completely?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So we have a motion. Is there a
second?
>> Okay, that amendment dies for lack of a
second. Okay. Uh I will move to
eliminate the entire section of B. Then
uh we'll get rid of all of B under
probable cause.
>> And then we it'll just skip directly for
grounds of issuance without any section
on probable cause.
>> Okay. Uh Mr. Leborn.
Oh, okay. Okay. We have a a motion on
the table to eliminate B. Is there a
second?
Okay, that motion dies for lack of a
second,
>> Madam Chairwoman.
>> Yes,
>> I didn't um
second the amendments made by my
colleague from W three
because I do think, as I've stated
earlier, I do think there is a place for
um routine periodic or area inspections
of commercial properties. And as I said,
as a one that owns a commercial
property, I don't think they've ever
been unreasonable in doing their
inspections of my my business. So, if it
will make people feel better, Madam
Chairwoman, in in uh section B1 at the
routine, periodic or area inspections, I
would like to insert the words of
commercial properties are satisfied with
respect to the particular property.
>> I would second that.
Um,
thank you, Dr. Can you repeat that one
more time, please?
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would like section
B1 to read reasonable legislative or
administrative standards for conducting
a routine periodic or area inspection of
commercial properties are satisfied with
respect to to the particular property.
>> Okay. So we
>> sure to madam chairwoman I said to the
particular commercial property
>> to the particular
>> particular community
commercial properties. Okay. So we have
a first and a second.
>> I would like to amend the amendment.
>> Okay. to read that reasonable
legislative or administrative standards
for conducting a routine periodic or
area inspection are satisfied with
respect to the particular commercial um
property or an open building permit.
>> Second.
>> Okay, we have a motion and a second to
add or open building to the end of that
sentence.
Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Is that uh
amendment to the amendment acceptable to
the
>> I think we have to vote on it.
>> I know they do that in the legislature,
but by Robert's rules of order, we have
to vote on it.
>> All right. Well, I just wanted to uh
first
>> make that clear. We're getting a number
of things here and
>> obviously uh
>> we're very fancy.
>> An amendment to the amendment might be
confusing to some.
>> Okay,
>> thank you.
All right. So, um, we're going to go out
to the public for comment.
>> Um, Bailey Turner and I would move to
support both amendments as it draws a
clear and direct line in the sand that
protects civilians and their private
homes. Thank you.
Kathy Siglano. Um I'm just curious if
the word only um needs to be in there
just so that it does only be specific to
commercial and the permit open permit
buildings um or does residential need to
be exempt in that section because I
think I mean the biggest concern here is
residential.
Thank you. Um,
uh, Mr. Brody, could you weigh in on
that?
Madam Chairwoman, John Brody, city
attorney. Uh, I'm sorry to belabor it,
but can the amended amendment be stated
again because I didn't quite follow
that.
>> Do I have it?
>> I think one of us has it. Reasonable
legislative or administrative standards
for conducting a routine periodic area
inspection of commercial properties are
satisfied with respect to the particular
commercial property or to an open
building permit.
>> Uh I guess I would say to the property
or subject to an open u building permit.
um just to make
>> you said
>> and then um I'd have to defer to the to
the building official really because I
don't know the extent to which he would
rely on those sort of more routine
inspections in the context of
residential property. I think the
amendment as stated accomplishes the
goal of um at least the council as it's
been discussed maybe not some of the
public comment
>> Dr. Renie
>> but through you madam chairwoman to our
council
um Mr. Brody, if the if the purpose of
the
the amendment that we've started the
premise that we where we started with
this the amendment dated January 30th,
one of the limitations is to in the
event of an open building permit. To me,
this doesn't contradict that. It simply
reinforces the intent of the amendment
that came out of your office. So,
>> I would agree with that, M. Madam
Chairman.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairw.
Okay. Any other public comment?
>> Patricia McCoy, I would support the
amendment if it does, as worded, limit
it to only the um commercial property
because again, we all agreed commercial
properties need to be inspected
routinely so that they're safe. We all
agree on that. Um but we don't want
people coming into our homes for any
reason. So, as long as that is clear
without the word only because I kind of
thought it might need that, too. But,
um, as long as it is clear just to
commercial properties, I would support
that as well.
>> Thank you, Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um, Dr. Minister, you I just want to be
perfectly clear on this because my
intention of adding an open building
permit uh was not that that would be
limited to commercial buildings. So, is
that um was that your understanding?
>> I was just thinking open building from
the period.
>> I was too, not just limited to
commercial. So, I wanted to make sure
that we're being very transparent about
that that it would be a commercial
property or
any open building permit. So, you've
invited them that inspection into your
home. And I think there's somebody
online that has a comment.
Hey, go ahead,
>> Mr. Crossman. can go ahead and unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you. I This is Colin Crossman Ward
one. I think um uh with respect to the
commercial uh the uh I I I'm fine with
it as is, but I think I'd be a little
bit more comfortable if it said
commercial,
nonresidential
to make it abundantly clear that any
form of commercial enterprise is open.
But uh I wouldn't want someone to say
that uh someone's rented apartment is
suddenly subject to these inspections
because it is a commercial with respect
to the landlord and not the resident. Uh
and in addition um I think that it is
perfectly fair to say that a residential
is uh is open to these inspections if
there is an open building permit simply
because I mean I don't think this is
necessary. I think that once you have an
open permit you invited the inspectors
anyway. But if the belt and suspenders
is required here, I think it's perfectly
fair to have commercial and residential
read into the latter component.
>> Thank you, sir. Okay,
then we will go back up to the
committee.
>> Mr. Lbourne.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um we're
dealing with a lot of specific
terminology here that uh perhaps needs
interpretation and uh one of the
questions I have here although I
certainly support the intent of this
which I believe correctly reinforces
everything that is in the code. Uh I I
agree with that. But many of the
properties that I deal with and that uh
city deals with are uh residential homes
that have been abandoned
and that is uh perhaps uh should be
noted or perhaps is that's unnecessary.
I see uh the chief building inspector
here, but um there just no doubt that uh
the big problem usually is a abandoned
residential property and I'm curious
what uh the chief building official has
to say about that.
Madam Chairwoman, uh Tony Carlo, chief
building official. Um
a a single family residential structure
is covered under a code called the
international residential code.
Commercial properties are covered under
an international building code. They are
separate codes completely. Um
J um Mr. Laybornne is absolutely correct
in that the majority of the homes that
we deal with are single family and they
would fall into the residential code. Um
I I'm want to make sure you understand
I'm not speaking to how to modify the
amendment. I'm just wanting to make sure
there's clarity.
Um it might be helpful if when we're
talking about a single family
residential structure. If we're
concerned about that language, we might
want to include as governed or or as um
yeah, as governed by the International
Residential Code if we're trying to
delineate
if that's helpful.
>> Thank you, Chairwoman Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> I'm wondering because we this entire
ordinance starts out actually citing all
of these different um building codes.
Um, and I see the international
residential code is listed here as well.
I believe that the um, abandoned
housings housing that um, Councilman
Labbornne is concerned with would be
covered under B3
um, where an inspection is reasonably
necessary to determine, discover, or
verify the condition of the property or
structures for compliance with the
applicable laws of provided in this
chapter
under I'm sorry 1.28.020. 020.
>> Madam Chairwoman,
>> yes, Dr. Renie,
>> the two amendments, the amendment and
then the amendment to the amendment, it
t you may want to stay up um just to
confirm
are only in regard to B1, which is only
referring to routine, periodic, or area
inspections. So, you've already um our
to our chief building official, you've
already
pointed out that the building department
does not do routine periodic or
inspections. They only report to
complaints essentially. Is that correct,
mu? Um Dr. Renie, it is correct. We do
not the building department's function
and mandate is not to perform the
routine periodic and area inspections.
that's a function that would fall within
the IFC to the fire chief and the fire
department. The latter part of the
section uh with where it says with
respect to uh to commercial properties
that language would fall to our
department and the language for
residential properties would fall to our
department. So either the clarification
of residential could be advantageous or
even breaking that out of the commercial
property section potentially might be
helpful. Okay, but for the sake of the
amendments, I want people to understand
we are only talking about
routine periodic area inspections which
is generally done only by the fire
department for commercial properties.
>> Okay,
>> thank you. My questions have been
answered.
>> Great. Thank you. Um, Mr. Leborn,
any other discussion?
Okay. So, we have an amendment on the
table to add uh specific or particular
community properties and um
>> first one is to add the open
building
>> to Dr. Renie, do you have this all
written down that you would like to
share?
>> Sort of.
>> Can you get it out of your head?
>> All right. Okay. The amendment was to
add of commercial properties
um inspection of commercial property is
satisfied with respect to the particular
commercial property
and that was the original amendment. The
amendment to that is to add
>> um or
>> open building permit for open building
permit
>> for an open building permit of any
property
>> voting on right now is
>> correct is to add the open building
permit.
>> Okay. So is everybody clear on that?
>> Going to go with yes. Okay. All those in
favor please signify by saying I. I
>> opposed.
>> Okay. So, that amendment carries.
>> Now, we're to the amendment, the main
the amendment that added of commercial
properties to the particular commercial
property.
>> Okay.
Uh
Mr. Oh, you don't have a thing. Dr.
Aldridge, do you have anything on that?
>> No, I'm just waiting.
>> Okay. Well, let's vote. Um so everyone
in favor of adding the or the particular
commu commercial properties uh signify
by saying I I
>> and oppose by no.
>> Okay, that carries. Chairwoman Nimmons,
I have one last amendment which would be
to B2
um adding the um sentence that uh at the
end that where it would say there is
probable cause to believe that a
condition of nonconformity, violation,
or other circumstance requiring
corrective action exist with respect to
the designated property that causes an
immediate risk to public health and/or
safety.
Madam chairwoman, I will second for the
sake of discussion.
>> So um Oops. So let's Does anybody have
any questions or make a comment about
that? reason uh to add that would be
really simply to uh make sure that there
is that sense of urgency and that's why
we're adding that that it's not um
something that could wait or be taken
care of later that there is a sense of
urgency. Somebody's chimney is about to
fall in their neighbor's house, whatever
that what whatever that looks like, but
there is that uh urgency that is um
necessitates this administrative warrant
being processed.
Okay.
So, let's open that up for public
comment.
>> You know, I had to let me just Patricia
McCoy, I would support this amendment
because it's not just fishing like, oh,
your grass is too tall. We're going to
come inspect everything or searching for
things. It shows there isn't an
immediate danger. So, I would be okay
with that.
>> Thank you. Anybody else?
>> John Brody, city attorney. Um, I guess I
just would note that none of the
nuisance provisions of the code are part
of this. So, there's certainly no danger
that your grass is going to be too long
and somebody's going to show up at your
house with a warrant. Um but secondarily
um I would just note for the committee's
consideration that the the language
that's being proposed sort of collapses
the exigency doctrine into the warrant
requirement. The ex exigency docu uh
doctrine being an exception to the
warrant requirement. So, if there's an
immediate uh risk of harm, then law
enforcement or the person that would
otherwise have to get a warrant can
forego that and can go onto the property
and address that immediate risk or
immediate harm. Um, by inserting this
idea of immediate risk, I I question how
a court is going to try to interpret
that. Is immediate risk the same as
immediate harm? Um, I I don't know. And
then again, um I I I guess I just
question um how a judge would would
grapple with that terminology given that
we have this entirely other doctrine out
there that talks about when you don't
need a warrant. So um I would just offer
that for your consideration.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
I wanted to second this for the sake
sake of discussion. I um am opposed to
the amendment and a couple things that
come to mind when I think about it. If I
think about my colleague from Ward One's
concern about abandoned buildings and we
should all be
worried about abandoned buildings. To
me, um
if there's an abandoned building on my
block,
I want it dealt with. But as I read
this,
if if it it's not going to be dealt with
until it becomes an immediate danger to
my block, which means it's caught on
fire or something like that. So, I don't
think this works in that case. I think
we all want that dealt with before it
becomes an immediate danger. Um, if
there are,
I don't know, some of you now believe
this, but there are some disreputable
contractors
working in the community. And if they're
doing if they have open building permits
and they are not um not doing work
properly, again, for something to become
an immediate danger to the neighborhood,
to me, it means that there has to be
something other than the fact that
they're doing it improperly that would
require you to get that inspection. So,
to me, I cannot support this. So, thank
you, Madam Chairwoman.
Chairwoman Emmens,
>> Dr. or yeah, Dr. Aldrich.
>> Um, I did want to respond to my
colleague that and remind him that in
this section B 1.208
or 1.28.020B,
it's any one of those three um items 1,
two, or three um is probable cause exist
if any one of those three exist. So, it
wouldn't necessarily um
forego that that abandoned property next
door to his house would um not meet the
um threshold for an administrative
warrant.
>> Madam Chairman,
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> thank you. Um
I'm not an attorney
and so I don't really
choose to try to interpret the law here,
but I do follow uh the understanding
that I believe the city attorney just
brought forward of those circumstances.
And I can tell you that this is
unnecessary.
I could take you out and anyone who's
interested probably this afternoon and
show you five abandoned properties.
Five abandoned properties that are not
that have been sitting there in some
cases literally for years.
It's not it's not an emergent situation
that it seems to be the intent of this
amendment.
Um, and I recognize that we want to be
careful about what we do.
But in this discussion we've had so far,
including on postponement,
I've heard an awful lot
from various people and in emails and
phone calls and uh
that they're concerned as well about
abandoned properties,
but
there's not one on every U street,
but there are a number of them and
they're not emergencies.
Well, I guess you could uh certainly
that could be developed into a criminal
emergency with the people that choose to
squat in them, but of course that's a
criminal matter of that individual.
These buildings
deserve attention
and they deserve and I'm I'm very glad,
Madame Chairman, and other members of
the committee that we're having this
discussion so that we can really um
come to understand and focus more
clearly on these really really difficult
situations. We need uh to look at that
in our upcoming budget. We need to be
able to work through what basically our
uh property rights. We can't just
bulldoze the building even though it's
in is a harm to the neighborhood and in
the shape that has been referred to
here. It's literally falling down. Um we
can't just go do that and we don't just
go do that and this takes a long time.
So, Madame Chairman, have we closed
public comment?
>> We've closed public comment, sir.
>> Announce that he's talking on another
subject. You should allow Michael White.
>> He's on the amendment.
>> Yeah. But you should allow, if he's
going to make a comment, but due respect
to you, Madam Chairman, you ought to
give myself a chance to respond to what
he says about us as a city going in and
doing something. And uh if it's not
appropriate, I can refer to you a
building that was done by the city
downtown over 20 years ago. And anybody
in this room can dispute it, but I would
say Mr. Leborn, the city has done things
with the building without every
dotted eye and cross tea. In all due
respect to Mr. labor and if it's
unappropriate to talk at this time, I
will
safely say that I would share my ex my
knowledge of this with Mr. Leborn after
the meeting and I will do that.
>> Thank you, Mr. White.
>> Madam Chairman,
>> yes.
Well, I'm not sure what happened 20
years ago downtown,
but I'm darn sure aware of what's
happening right this afternoon.
And so, um I think that we have uh
gone through this uh
substitute. I think we've made uh some
changes that were necessary, but this
this particular language as was noted by
our city attorney is is really not
necessary
and could possibly I mean and we've
heard how much discussion have we heard,
Madame Chairman and members of the
committee of what could happen
what could happen in the future, what
could happen uh with this particular
ordinance. Well, a lot of things could
happen, but we certainly don't want to
have language in this um substitute
that could possibly cause confusion. And
so I speak against uh this motion. And
and I'd also point out, Madam Chairman,
that
since this got personal a little bit, I
I want to recognize that I've known this
individual that just spoke for many
years and he was a dedicated employee of
the city of Cheyenne and uh uh knows
what he's talking about, but we're
talking about today, not 20 years ago.
Thank you,
>> Mr. Leborn. And I think I think I did
miss opening it for public comment with
this last amendment. We had a lot of
amendments coming forward. So,
go ahead, Kathy Cigano. Um, I would just
like to have some clarification in
regards to abandoned buildings. Um, what
the city's process is with that? Do they
get red tagged? If they do, who follows
up with that red tag? Is it the city
attorney? Is it our police department?
Is it the fire chief? depending on I
guess why it's being red tagged. Um with
Dr. Aldridge is with her amendment. I
mean this this lays out a public safety
concern.
So if there has been a previous public
safety concern and a building has been
redtagged because of it being abandoned,
what's the process after that? Is
someone failing to do their job?
I would just like clarification.
>> Thank you.
Um, Jennifer,
>> Mr. Crossman, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Hi, Colin Crossman Ward One. Um, I am
interested in this one because if I read
it, you have, let me call it up on my
phone here. Um, you have a situation
where it says, let's see, B2 here.
Oh, come on.
There is probable cause to believe that
a condition of nonconformity, violation,
or other circumstances requiring
corrective action exists.
If a building code is updated,
then there is automatically
probable cause to believe that a
condition of non-conformity exists. Now,
it may not require corrective action,
but the condition exists because uh
anything that is was built in the
previous building code, it now has some
non-conformities. Otherwise, you
wouldn't update the building code to
begin with. So, that's what the purpose
of adding the life safety component is.
And if there is serious concern about
this reading out abandoned properties,
then that could easily be fixed by
adding a sentence about abandoned
properties separately or a separate
provision about abandoned properties. I
don't think anyone here or any of the
public seriously have a problem with the
inspection of
uh you know abandoned properties. The
issue is coming into people's homes. And
if you have the ability that any belief
of nonconformity that could require a
corrective action exists, well, you're
going to have every single property in
the city fits that description after a
certain period of time. So that kind of
swallows the entire rule without some
sort of break on it being required for
life safety
be or uh and if you're worried about the
abandoned properties, put that in
another sentence.
Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Crosslin. Any
other public comment?
Okay, we are back with the committee.
Dr. Renie,
>> Madam Chairwoman, I have a question for
the maker of the amendment. If um so
it's the addition of that causes an
immediate risk to public health
andor safety.
So, does that go after designated
property or after or?
>> It goes after designated property before
or.
>> Okay. Madam, Madam Chairwoman, I as I
kind of alluded to earlier, I don't
think I could support this if it went at
because I think the people that even
though it has been pointed out to me by
my colleague that made the amendment
that the condition of nonconformity
violation or other circumstance still
exists, I think the people that have
spoke for it read it as that that causes
immediate risk to public and health and
safety supersedes the others. if it
followed the or was just another portion
of the list, I could support it. So,
um, but as she is making an I will vote
now
to a separate item.
>> Yeah, I would
>> um
>> do you want to vote on this first?
>> Can't if he's going to amend it.
>> Well, we can vote on and then I can
bring it back the amendment. Okay,
>> maybe that's cleaner than having
amendment on an amendment.
>> Okay, so the amendment is that after
designated property that causes an
immediate risk to health andor safety.
All those in favor of that amendment,
please signify by saying I
>> I
>> and opposed.
>> No.
>> Okay. Motion or the amendment fails.
>> Madam Chairwoman,
>> Dr. Renie,
>> I would like to amend B2
um to use the language that was proposed
by my colleague that causes an immediate
risk to public health andor safety
period to follow the or at the very end
of of paragraph B2.
>> So, Dr. Renie, just for clarification,
that would be a new number three. No, it
would be number two would read there is
probable cause to believe that a
condition of nonconformity violation or
other circumstance requiring corrective
action exists with respect to the
designated property or that causes an
immediate risk to public health andor
safety.
>> Okay. Is there a second?
>> I'll second.
>> Okay. We're going to go Oh, would you
like to talk about that first? Okay. No,
I think I've made my point earlier.
Thank you.
>> Okay, so we'll go back out for public
comment on that addition,
which is the same language we just spoke
about.
Okay.
Um, so I'm going to close public comment
and come back to the committee.
Any other discussion?
Representative or Councilman Lebornne,
did you have something? Okay. Okay. Um
then let's go ahead and do a vote on
this. So everyone who is in favor of
adding that causes an immediate risk to
health and safety after or please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
>> No.
>> Okay. That amendment passes.
Any other amendments?
Ready to vote on the Okay.
substitute. Okay. So substitute as
amended.
>> We are on the substitute
from January 30th as amended.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Anyone opposed?
Okay, that ordinance passes.
>> Excuse me.
>> Yes.
>> What? Now we're on the main recommend
approval.
>> Now we're back on the main motion to
recommend approval.
>> All those do I have to go back out?
Okay. All those in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
Okay. Now it's passed
>> as amended
>> and goes on to third reading as amended.
>> Okay.
Number seven, ordinance third reading.
Annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, various tracks of land
completely surrounded by current city
limits, Situate and eastern Cheyenne,
generally located south of Story
Boulevard, east of Powder House Road,
north of Del Range Boulevard, and west
of Ridge Road.
>> Okay. Is there staff report?
Chairwoman and members of the committee,
Conor White Planning and Development
Department. Uh this annexation, we're on
third reading. This is for basically
north of Walmart and everything. Um and
east of Converse Avenue. Uh there has
not been any additional public comment
on this item. Um and I'm available for
any questions.
>> Okay. Is there any public comment?
Okay. Seeing none,
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a move to approve by Dr.
um Aldrich and a second by Dr. Renie.
Is there any comments?
Okay. All those who um in favor of
second reading of this ordinance, please
say I.
>> I.
>> And opposed.
All right.
Number eight, ordinance third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classifications of AG,
agricultural and MR, medium density
residential for land annex to the city
of Cheyenne, generally located south of
Story Boulevard, east of Powderhouse
Road, north of Del Range Boulevard, and
west of Ridge Road.
>> All right, staff report, please.
>> Chairwoman, members of committee,
counterweight, planning and development
department. This assigned zoning goes
along with that annexation. Um, with any
annexation, we have to assign city zones
and this is on third reading and I am
available for any questions.
>> Is there any public comment?
Okay. Comments by the committee.
>> Madame Chairwoman, I would move to
approve on third and final.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved and seconded. Do we have
any other comments?
Okay. All those in favor, please signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> And opposed.
Okay.
>> Number nine, ordinance third reading,
amending 5.7.3
accessory dwelling units of the Cheyenne
Unified Development Code to remove owner
occupancy and adjust parking
requirements for accessory dwellings and
make conforming amendments to the
definitions of an accessory dwelling and
semi-attached dwelling. Under 1.4.4, for
descriptions of uses of land and
buildings.
>> Okay. Staff report.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
my name is Seth Lloyd. I'm with the City
of Shine Planning and Development
Department. Um the ordinance in front of
you amends our unified development code
to make ADUs allowed um with no owner
occupancy requirement. There will be a
small changes to the code to affect
this. Um, also it allows for parking um
to be satisfied not necessarily on a
discrete portion of the lot. Just um
make sure there's parking available
somewhere on the lot for the ADU. Um
there have been no changes to this
ordinance since it was on uh second
reading. Um it did pass second reading
and I've had no other public comments um
since between second reading and today.
But I'm available for any questions.
Okay.
>> Any public comment?
>> Okay. No questions from
>> No. Good. Do we have any questions? And
does someone want to make a motion?
>> I would move to approve.
>> Okay, we have a motion and a second.
Um, all those in favor,
>> Madam Chairman.
>> Yes, sir.
>> I'm just going to say what I said to
council last week on second reading. I
understand why we did this when you
could add an accessory dwelling unit
when the property owner lived there. I
thought that was a great move. This I do
not think is a good move. I think we
will see more of our areas um more of
our neighborhoods where places are
bought and then an ADU is added and they
will both become rentals. And as I've
watched in I live in the Buffalo Ridge
area just near it and as I've watched
over the years as more of those homes
have become rentals. Um the maintenance
is not always the same as it is with
with the property owner living there. So
I think this is a bad move. I think in
the long term it will hurt some of our
neighborhoods in Cheyenne.
>> Are there any other comments?
Okay. So we have a fir a motion and a
second. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And opposed?
>> No.
>> The recommendation for Monday's meeting
will be to approve on third reading.
>> Number 10. Ordinance, second reading,
creating chapter 8.72 private displays
on public property to prohibit the
unauthorized you unauthorized use of
public property for specified private
displays.
>> Um, staff.
>> Staff report. Thank you. Chairwoman
Emmens. Um this I brought forward this
ordinance um because I had been
contacted by um multiple constituents
concerned about um the displays on
public property and on private property
when someone is um killed at a site in
our community. In ward three, we have uh
such a memorial in our ward that um in
March that young woman uh that was
tragically killed will have uh that
memorial will have been in place for 5
years. Um we also unfortunately in Ward
three had have had multiple motorcycle
accidents resulting in deaths. Um one
has a display uh which falls on private
property. One has a display that falls
on a state highway. Um it this these
displays while um serving a purpose I
think a needed purpose for the family um
sometimes make it really difficult for
our um
crews that do the mowing of those areas
to be able to work around them. They're
concerned about damaging those displays.
I've talked with our um staff about
that. We've also had a question about
from constituents about the fairness or
the consistency um with these public
memorials. Um I had asked Mr. Hopinson
um from our city attorney's office to
work on this um back in November um but
really delayed bringing it forward until
I was able to contact the family of the
um young woman who was killed on Nation
Way. um after visiting with her family u
multiple family members um really felt
like this uh and discussing why there
was a need for this um I feel confident
that um this is something our community
needs and while I recognize the need to
recognize um a tragic accident of an
individual there are other ways in which
they those can be memorialized
um the state highway department for
those killed along state highways has a
memorial sign that can be put into place
at no cost to the family. Um, and maybe
that's something that, you know,
somewhere in the future the city of
Cheyenne would want to pursue. But at
this point in time, I'm looking for a
way to make this consistent um by
allowing a memorial to be displayed for
7 days um and then having a process for
which to be able to remove those
memorials. Um, so it's consistent and
while still giving those families a
sense of closure.
>> Okay. Are there any questions for
the the sponsor?
Any questions or any comments from the
public?
Nobody online.
Madam Chair, Seth with the City of Shine
Planning and Development Department. Um,
I have some concerns about the use,
general use of public property and the
general use of display as outlined in
the ordinance as it stands. Um, we
occasionally get people who will go up
and down our streets and put in
temporary signs with no regards to rules
or regulations. Um, historically we've
had crews just go ahead and remove those
immediately as soon as they're there. um
uh and sometimes they're in parks
without any approvals or any um uh
respect to regulations. Um leaving them
up for 7 days would be beneficial for
these folks um before we could remove
them. Um because it it's nearly certain
these folks know that what they're doing
is illegal. They just feel like I I'll
get it up for as long as I can get it up
and when it gets removed it gets
removed. Um so I have concerns that
those will be considered a type of
display. um these temporary signs. Um I
also uh have a little bit of a uh
concern about the definition of public
property. Um say the municipal buildings
parcel that the city owns versus a
public right ofway. Um, generally my
opinion is that if it's on a on a
city-owned parcel such as the municipal
building parcel, um, it becomes like any
property owner of the city has certain
rights to not allow things to happen on
their land. Um, if someone were to put a
display on my property of any sort,
whether that's a temporary sign or
memorial or whatever, and I didn't want
it there. As property owner, I can just
remove that. Um, I mean, I remove trash
from my yard all the time with wind and
Cheyenne. It happens. I'm not going to
consider, oh, that's a display that I
have to wait to remove. Um, but I feel
like the city should have that um
ability as a property owner. Um, when it
comes to properties actually owned by
the city, I realize the public rightway
is a little bit of a different issue,
but um say a public park or the
municipal building um I don't know, a
BOPU facility or something like that. Um
I I feel like as property owner, the
city should have certain property owner
rights for their properties as well. So,
I just have a couple concerns there. Um,
I'm available for questions if there are
any.
>> Madam Chairwoman,
>> Dr. Ren,
>> since Mr. Lloyd is here, my
understanding,
pardon me, and I was going to ask this
anyway, um, we currently have prohibit
prohibitions of signs, whether it be
business advertising or campaign signs
that are not only prohibited in public
parks, but in public right away.
Correct,
>> Mr. Mr. You, Madam Chair, that is
correct. We do not allow um signage in
the right ofway. That is a those are
prohibited signs. I would say that if a
temporary sign is possibly encroaching
on the public rightway at a single
family home where there's an attached
sidewalk, you don't really know where
the public rideway is. We we're we're
flexible on those as as long as the
property owner adjacent is the one who's
uh authorizing that sign.
>> Correct. And that's the way we've my
understanding is we've practiced it that
way for years now. So um thank you Mr.
Lloyd. Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Okay. Um,
Councilman Roy um, Lebornne.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman.
Well,
obviously this is a extremely sensitive
matter um that
probably is uh way different than other
things that we deal with and is
not
that frequent. But uh my personal
observation is that over the years it's
become more and more common for these
type of uh memorials to occur and their
purpose uh
is I assume to be to notice the passing
of that individual and possibly some
sometimes I've seen pictures I've seen
different uh
objects that were associated with that
individual
and I've seen uh something to do with uh
the wreck itself. So I do recognize that
this is an issue that uh we probably
ought to take a look at.
I would refer to the comments I heard
earlier from my colleague from W three
that uh the state highway department has
has had to deal with this
and they have a memorial plaque that
they
authorize and place at those sites. And
I think probably
part of the whole reason that people do
make these memorials is to uh warn
people or point out a danger or a
thought process should be involved with
that particular area.
But unless we have some further
uh ability to memorialize this, as the
state of Wyoming does, I don't think we
ought to be passing it on until we have
a better understanding of how they came
to their conclusion and why they
practiced that particular uh action. So,
um I
especially recognize uh I noticed one
memorial out on Nation Way, which is in
the median. Uh not it really is where uh
no one should be to begin with. And and
that area is one where we've had a
number of pedestrian uh accidents and
deaths. So, um I think the general
intent here is good. But I think it
needs some more uh thought and that
would be particularly referencing how
and why the state of Wyoming came to the
conclusion that they did. Thank you.
>> Okay. Um
>> we were on public comment when Mr. Lloyd
came up. We're still on it.
>> So no more. Is there any other public
comment here? We're going to close
public comment.
Um, Dr. Aldridge has a motion on the
table. Is
>> I would move to adopt.
>> Okay. Is there a second?
>> I'll second so that Dr. Aldridge can
discuss it.
>> Okay.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Thank you. Um, I would just encourage um
I understand that perhaps we need to I
and I will work with um Mr. Hopinson um
to remove the term advertising out of uh
8.72.020A.
Um I understand Mr. Labborn's um desire
that we have some sort of way to
memorialize
um these individuals or to have some
sort of um documentation if you will um
of those instances. Um but I believe
that um there is a need for us to be
able to provide some sort of um limited
um limitation to the these public
displays and some sort of guidance. So
because right now our um city employees
have no authority um or don't feel they
have any authority to remove these
public displays um when they run across
those in their day-to-day work. So, I
would encourage my colleagues to um
support this and um we'll work with Mr.
Hopkinson should it pass to um corrected
the deficiencies that have been uh
pointed out today.
>> Madam Chairwoman,
>> yes, Dr. Renie,
>> I personally don't find these displays
bothersome.
Um so, I don't know that I will support
the ordinance at this point. However, I
guess I'd like to hear from either um
our director of public works or our
director of CRA. And I mean, in my 27
years up here, nobody's said this is an
issue for us. Can we we need we need a
solution. So, um I you know, sometime
they can send me an email in the next
week and tell me their thoughts on it.
That's fine. Unless Vicki wants to speak
now.
>> Vicky Vicky Neich public works. I have
had our uh street alley division request
um guidance on this um the one on nation
way is especially big. It's getting
bigger all the time. Um so it is a it is
a concern. I would say that for us it's
a concern just in the rightway not on
other public lands. I don't think we've
had that problem. And I agree that it
would be um the municipal building, for
example, if they put a sign, somebody
put a sign up here, it should be treated
as Seth described, we should be able to
go out there and take that down
immediately. Um but it would be good to
have guidance on what we should do with
these displays so that people don't be
that people aren't angry with us.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> Madam Chairwoman, to Director Nichek.
So, do we just mow around them now? Is
that And leave them alone?
>> Do you madam chair? Yes, that's correct.
We mow around them.
>> Okay. And obviously we don't get in the
middle with a weed eater and clean up
the grass growing up around the display.
>> Um through you chair. We don't use weed
eaters. We use large flail mower. So
you'd have CR may um I'm not sure how
they handle it.
>> Okay. So my but as I'm envisioning it,
if you mow around it, then if the grass
grows up in amongst the memorial, that's
up to whoever put the memorial there.
They're currently
>> correct.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Okay. Any other comments?
Okay. So, we have a motion on the table
and a second. All those in favor of the
ordinance, um please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay. the uh recommendation there will
be no recommendation to the commit to
the uh council on Monday night and with
that there's no more business so we are
adjourned. Thank you all for being very
patient. Go ahead.